Your support will help MIT
OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational
resources for free.
To make a donation or view
additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: I want to
pick up exactly where
I left off last time.
When I was talking about
various sins one can
commit with statistics.
And I had been talking about
the sin of data enhancement,
where the basic idea there is,
you take a piece of data, and
you read much more into
it than it implies.
In particular, a very common
thing people do with data
is they extrapolate.
I'd given you a
couple of examples.
In the real world, it's often
not desirable to say that I
have a point here, and a point
here, therefore the next
point will surely be here.
And we can just extrapolate
in a straight line.
We before saw some examples
where I had an algorithm to
generate points, and we fit a
curve to it, used the curve to
predict future points, and
discovered it was
nowhere close.
Unfortunately, we often see
people do this sort of thing.
One of my favorite stories is,
William Ruckelshaus, who was
head of the Environmental
Protection Agency in
the early 1970s.
And he had a press conference,
spoke about the increased use
of cars, and the decreased
amount of carpooling.
He was trying to get people to
carpool, since at the time
carpooling was on the way down,
and I now quote, "each car
entering the central city,
sorry, in 1960," he said, "each
car entering the central
city had 1.7 people in it.
By 1970. this had dropped
to less than 1.2.
If present trends continue, by
1980, more than 1 out of every
10 cars entering the city will
have no driver." Amazingly
enough, the press reported this
as a straight story, and talked
about how we would be
dramatically dropping.
Of course, as it happened,
it didn't occur.
But it's just an example of,
how much trouble you can
get into by extrapolating.
The final sin I want to talk
about is probably the most
common, and it's called the
Texas sharpshooter fallacy.
Now before I get into that, are
any of you here from Texas?
All right, you're
going to be offended.
Let me think, OK, anybody
here from Oklahoma?
You'll like it.
I'll dump on Oklahoma, it
will be much better then.
We'll talk about the Oklahoma
sharpshooter fallacy.
We won't talk about the
BCS rankings, though.
So the idea here is a
pretty simple one.
This is a famous marksman who
fires his gun randomly at the
side of a barn, has a bunch of
holes in it, then goes and
takes a can of paint and draws
bullseyes around all the places
his bullets happened to hit.
And people walk by the barn
and say, God, he is good.
So obviously, not a good
thing, but amazingly easy
to fall into this trap.
So here's another example.
In August of 2001, a paper
which people took seriously
appeared in a moderately
serious journal called
The New Scientist.
And it announced that
researchers in Scotland had
proven that anorexics are
likely to have been
born in June.
I'm sure you all knew that.
How did how did
they prove this?
Or demonstrate this?
They studied 446 women.
Each of whom had been
diagnosed anorexic.
And they observed that
about 30 percent more than
average were born in June.
Now, since the monthly average
of births, if you divide this
by 12, it's about 37,
that tells us that 48
were born in June.
So at first sight, this seems
significant, and in fact if you
run tests, and ask what's the
likelihood of that many more
being born in 1 month, you'll
find that it's quite unlikely.
In fact, you'll find the
probability of this happening
is only about 3 percent, of it
happening just by accident.
What's wrong with
the logic here?
Yes?
STUDENT: They only studied
diagnosed anorexics.
PROFESSOR: No, because they
were only interested in the
question of when are anorexics
born, so it made sense
to only study those.
Now maybe you're right, that we
could study that, in fact, more
people are born in June period.
That could be true.
This would be one of the
fallacies we looked
at before, right?
That there's a lurking variable
which is just that people are
more likely to be born in June.
So that's certainly
a possibility.
What else?
What else is the flaw?
Where's the flaw in this logic?
Well, what did they do?
They participated in the
Oklahoma sharpshooter fallacy.
What they did is, they looked
at 12 months, they took the
months with the most births in
it, which happened to be
June, and calculated the
probability of 3 percent.
They didn't start with the
hypothesis that it was June.
They started with 12 months,
and then they drew a
bullseye around June.
So the right question to ask
is, what's the probability, not
that June had 48 babies, but
that at least one of the
12 months had 48 babies.
That probability is a lot to
higher than 3 percent, right?
In fact, it's about 30 percent.
So what we see is, again
perfectly reasonable
statistical techniques,
but not looking at
things in the right way.
And answering the
wrong question.
That make sense to everybody?
And you can see why people can
fall into this trap, right?
It was a perfectly sensible,
seemingly sensible argument.
So the moral of this particular
thing is, be very careful about
looking at your data, drawing a
conclusion, and then saying how
probable was that
to have occurred?
Because again, you're probably,
or maybe, drawing the
bullseye around something
that's already there.
Now if they had taken another
set of 446 anorexics, and again
June was the month, then
there would be some
credibility in it.
Because they would have started
with the hypothesis, not that
there existed a month, but that
June was particularly likely.
But then they would have to
also check and make sure that
June isn't just a popular
month to be born, as
was suggested earlier.
All right, I could go on
and on with this sort of
thing, it's kind of fun.
But I won't.
Instead I'm going to
torture you with yet
one more simulation.
You may be tempted at this
point to just zone out.
Try not to.
And as an added incentive for
you to pay attention, I'm
going to warn you that this
particular simulation will
appear in the final,
or a variant of it.
And what we'll be doing is,
early next week we'll be
distributing code, which we'll
ask you to study, about two or
three pages of code, and then
on the final we'll be asking
you questions about the code.
Not that you have to
memorize it, we'll
give you a copy of it.
But you should understand
it before you walk in
to take the final.
Because there will not be time
to look at that code for the
first time during the quiz, and
figure out what it's doing.
OK, so let's look at it.
I should also warn you that
this code includes some Python
concepts, at least one,
that you have not yet seen.
We'll see it briefly today.
This is on purpose, because one
of the things I hope you have
learned to do this semester, is
look up things you don't know,
and figure out what they do.
What they mean.
Because we obviously can't, in
any course, or even any set of
courses, tell you everything
you'll ever want
to know in life.
So intentionally, we've seeded
some things in this program
that will be unfamiliar, so
during the time you're studying
the program, get online, look
it up, figure out what they do.
If you have trouble, we will
be having office hours, where
you can go and get some help.
But the TAs will expect you
to have at least tried to
figure it out yourself.
Yeah?
STUDENT: Will the
final be open note?
PROFESSOR: Final will be
open book, open notes,
just like the quizzes.
It will be the first two hours
of the allotted time, we won't
go the whole 3 hours, OK?
So it won't be hugely
longer than the quizzes.
It would be a
little bit longer.
And again, very much in the
same style of the quizzes.
All right, let's look at this.
Let's assume that you've won
the lottery, and have serious
money that you foolishly wish
to invest in the stock market.
There are two basic strategies
to choose from, in investing.
You can either have what's
called an indexed portfolio,
or a managed portfolio.
Indexed portfolios, you
basically say, I want to own
all of the stocks that there
are, and if the stock market
goes up, I make money, if
the stock market goes
down, I lose money.
I'm not going to be thinking
I'm clever, and can pick
winners and losers, I'm
just betting on the
market as a whole.
They're attractive, in that
a, they don't require
a lot of thought.
And b, they have what's called
a low expense ratio, since
they're easy to implement, you
don't pay anyone to be
brilliant to implement
if for you.
So they're very low fees.
A managed portfolio, you find
somebody you think is really
smart, and you pay them a fair
amount of money, and in return
they assert that they will pick
winners for you, and in fact,
you will outperform
the stock market.
And if it goes up 6 percent,
well you'll go up 10 percent
or more, and if it goes down,
don't worry, I'm so smart
your stocks won't go down.
There's a lot of debate
about which is the
better of these two.
And so now we're going to try
and see if we can write a
simulation that will give us
some insight as to which of
these might be better or worse.
All right, so that's
the basic problem.
Now, as we know, and by the way
we're not going to write a
perfect simulation here,
because we're going to try and
do it in 40 minutes,
or 30 minutes.
And it would take at least an
hour do a perfect simulation
of the stock market.
All right.
First thing we need to do is
have some sort of a theory.
When we did the spring, we had
this theory of Hooke's Law that
told us something, and we built
a simulation, or built some
tools around that theory.
Now we need to think about a
model of the stock market.
And the model we're going
to use is based on what's
called the Efficient
Market Hypothesis.
So the moral here, again, is
whenever you're doing an
implementation of a simulation,
you do need to have some
underlying theory
about the model.
What this model asserts
is that markets are
informationally efficient.
That is to say, current prices
reflect all publicly known
information about each stock,
and therefore are unbiased.
That if people thought that the
stock was underpriced, well
people would buy more of it in
the price would have
risen already.
If people thought the stock was
overpriced, well, people would
have tried to sell it, and
it would have come down.
So this is a very popular
theory, believed by
many famous economists
today, and in the past.
And says, OK, that effectively
means that the market
is memoryless.
OK, that it doesn't matter
what the price of the
stock was yesterday.
Today, it's priced given the
best-known information, and
so tomorrow it's equally
likely to go up or down.
Relative to the whole
market, right?
It's well known that over
periods of multiple
decades, the market has a
tendency to go up.
And so there's an upward bias
to the stock market, contrary
to what you may have
seen recently.
But that no particular stock
is more or less likely to
outperform the market, because
all the information is
incorporated in the price.
And that leads to a notion
of being able to model
the market, how?
How would you model individual
stocks if you believe
this hypothesis?
Somebody?
What's going to happen?
STUDENT: Random walk.
PROFESSOR: Yes, exactly right.
So we would model it
as a random walk.
In fact, there's a very famous
book called A Random Walk Down
Wall Street, that was one of
the first to make
this hypothesis.
Now later, we may decide to
abandon this model, but for
the moment let's accept that.
And let's think about how we're
going to build the simulation.
Whenever I think about how to
build an interesting program,
and I hope whenever you think
about it, the first thing I
think about is, what are the
classes I might want to
have, what are the types?
And it seems pretty obvious
that at least two of the
things I'm going to want
are stock and market.
After all, I'm going to try and
build a simulation of the stock
market, so I might as well have
the notion of a market, and
probably the notion of a stock.
Which should I implement first?
Well, my usual style of
programming would be to
implement the one that's
lowest down in the
hierarchy, near the bottom.
I won't be able to show you
what a market does unless I
have stocks, but I can look at
what an individual stock does
without having a market.
So why do I implement
this first?
Because it will be
easier to unit test.
I can build class stock, and I
can test class stock, before
I have a class market.
So now let's look at it.
Clean up the desktop
a little bit.
This is similar to, but not
identical to, what you
have in your handout.
All right, so there's
class stock.
And I'm going to initialize
it, create them, with
an opening price.
When a stock is first
listed in the market, it
comes with some price.
I'm gonna keep as part of each
stock, it's history of prices,
which we can initialize, well,
I've initialized it as empty,
but that's probably the
wrong thing, right?
I probably should have had it
being the, starting here,
right, the opening price.
Now comes an interesting part.
Self dot distribution.
Well, I lied to you a little
bit in my description of
what it meant to have the
Efficient Market Hypothesis.
I said that no stock is likely
to outperform the market or
underperform the market.
But it's not quite true,
because typically what they
actually do that, is they
say it's adjusted for risk.
It's clear that some stocks are
more volatile than others.
If you will buy stock in an
electrical utility which has a
guaranteed revenue stream,
because no matter how bad the
economy gets, a lot of people
still use electricity, you
don't expect it to
fluctuate a lot.
If you buy stock in a high tech
company, that sells things on
the internet, you might expect
it to fluctuate enormously.
Or if you buy stock in a
retailer, you might expect
it to go up or down more
dramatically with the economy,
and so in fact there is a
notion of risk, and I'm not
going to do this in this
simulation, but usually people
have to be paid to take risk.
And so it's usually the case
that you can get a higher
return if you're willing
to take more risk.
We might or might not have
time to come back to that.
But more generally, the point
is, that each stock actually
behaves a little
bit differently.
There's a distribution
of how it would move.
So even if, on average, the
stock is expected to not move
at all from where it starts,
some stocks will be expected to
just trundle along without much
change, not very volatile.
And other stocks might jump
up and down a lot because
they're very volatile.
Even if the expected value
is the same, they'd
move around a lot.
So how can we model
this kind of thing?
Well, we've already looked
at the basic notion.
Last time we looked at the
notion, last lecture we looked
at the idea of a distribution.
And when we do a simulation,
we're pulling the samples
from some distribution.
It could be normal, everything,
that would be a Gaussian, where
if you recall there was a mean,
and a standard deviation, and
most values were going to
be close to the mean.
Especially if there is a
small standard deviation.
If there's a large standard
deviation it would be spread.
Or it could be uniform,
where every value was
equally probable.
We also looked at exponential.
So we're going to assign to
each stock, when we create
it, a distribution.
Some way of visualizing, or
thinking about, where we draw
the price changes from.
This gets us into a new
linguistic concept, which
we'll see down here.
You don't have this particular
code on your handout, you do
have a code that uses
the same concept.
So here's my unit
test procedure.
And here's where I'm going
to create distributions.
And I'm going to look at two.
A random-- a uniform,
and a Gaussian.
What lambda that does, it
creates on the fly a function,
as the program runs.
That I can then pass around.
So here, I'm going to look at
the thing random dot uniform,
for example, between minus
volatility and plus volatility.
So ignoring the lambda,
what do we expect random
dot uniform to do?
It has equally likely, in the
range from minus volatility
to plus volatility, it will
return any value in here.
But notice the previous
line, where I am
computing volatility.
If I wanted every stock to have
the same volatility, I could
just do that, if you will, at
the time I wrote my program.
But here I want it to be
determined, chosen at run time.
So first, I choose a volatility
randomly, from some
distribution of possible
volatilities from 0 to,
in this case, 0.2.
Think of this as the
percentage move per day.
So 2/10 of a percent,
would be the move here.
And then I'll create this
function, this distribution d
1, which will, whenever I call
it, give me a random, a
uniformly selected value
between minus and
plus volatility.
Then when I create the
stock, here, I can pass
it in, pass in d 1.
OK, it's a new concept.
I don't expect you'll all
immediately grab it, but you
will need to understand it
before the quiz comes along.
And then I could also do a
Gaussian one here, with the
mean of 0 and the standard
deviation of volatility
divided by 2.
Where do these
parameters come from?
I made them up out
of whole cloth.
Later we'll talk about how
1 could think about them
more intelligently.
Now what do I do with that?
All right, we'll see
that in a minute.
But people understand what
the basic idea here is.
Now, I can set the
price of a stock.
And when I do that, I'll
append it to history.
I can, oh, these have
got some remnants which
we really don't need.
I'll get rid of this which is
just an uninteresting thing.
And let's look at make move.
Because this is the
interesting thing.
Make move is what we call to
change the price of a stock,
at the beginning or end
of a day if you will.
So the first thing it does, is
it says, if self dot price is
0, I'm just going to return.
This is not the right
thing to do, by the way.
Again, there are
some bugs in here.
You won't find these bugs
in your handout, right?
Code is different
in the handout.
But I wanted to show these to
you so we could think about.
What I'm more interested in
here than in the result
of the simulation, is the
process of creating it.
So why did I put this here?
Why did I say if self dot
price equals 0 return?
Because the first time I wrote
the program, I didn't have
anything like that here, and a
stock could go to 0
and then recover.
Or even go to negative values.
Well we know stock prices
are never negative.
And in fact we know if the
price goes to 0, it's
delisted from the exchange.
So I said, all right, we better
make a special case of that. it
turns out, that this will be a
bug, and I want you to think
about why it's wrong for me
to put this check here.
The check needs to be somewhere
in the program, but this is
not the right place for it.
So think about why I
didn't leave it here.
OK, then we'll get the old
price, which we're going to try
and remember, and now comes
the interesting part.
We're going to try and
figure out how the
price should change.
So I'm first going to compute
something called the base move.
Think of this as kind of the
basis from which we'll be
computing the actual move.
I'll draw something from the
distribution, so this is
interesting, I'm now calling
self dot distribution, and
remember this will be
different for each stock.
It will return me some random
value from either the Gaussian
or the normal distribution.
With a different volatility for
the stocks because that was
also selected randomly,
plus some market bias.
Saying, well, the market on
average will go up a little
bit, or go down a little bit.
And then I'll set the new
price, if you will, self dot
price, to self dot price
times 1 plus the base move.
So notice what this says.
If the base move is 0, then
the price doesn't change.
So that makes sense.
Interesting question.
Why do you think I said self
dot price times 1 plus the base
move, rather than just adding
the base move to the stock,
price of the stock?
Again, the first time I coded
this, I had an addition there
instead of a multiplication.
What would the ramifications
of an addition there be?
That would say, how much the
stock changed is independent
of its current price.
And when I ran that it, I got
weird results, because we know
that a Google priced at, say,
300, is much more likely to
move by 10 points in a day than
a stock that's priced at $0.50.
So in fact, it is the case, if
you look at data, and by the
way, that's the way I ended up
setting a lot of these
parameters and playing with it,
was comparing what my
simulation said to
historical stock data.
And indeed it is the case that
the price of the stock, the
move, the amount of move,
tends to be proportional
to the price of the stock.
Expensive stocks move more.
Interestingly enough, the
percentage moves are not much
different between cheap
stocks and expensive stocks.
And that's why, I ended up
using a multiplicative factor,
rather than an additive factor.
This is again a general lesson.
As you build these kinds of
simulations, or anything like
this, you need to think through
whether things should be
multiplicative or additive.
Because you get very different
results, typically.
Multiplicative is what you want
to do if the amount of change
is proportional to the current
size, whether it's price or
anything else, and additive if
the change is independent of
the current value, typically,
is I think the general
way to think about it.
Now, you'll see this other
kind of peculiar thing.
So I've now set the price, and
then I've got this test here.
If mo, mo stands for momentum.
I'm now exploring the question
of whether or not stock prices
are indeed memoryless,
or the stock changes.
And the fancy word
for that is Poisson.
People often model things as
Poisson processes, which is to
say, processes in which past
behavior has no impact on
future behavior,
it's memoryless.
And in fact, that's what the
Efficient Market Hypothesis
purports to say.
It says that, since all the
information is in the current
price, you don't have to worry
about whether it went up or
down yesterday, to decide
what it's going to do today.
There are people who don't
believe that, and instead
argue that there is this
notion called momentum.
These are called
momentum investors.
And they say, what's most
likely to happen today, is
what happened yesterday.
Or more likely.
If the stock went up yesterday,
it's more likely to go up
today, than if it didn't
go up yesterday.
So I wasn't sure which religion
I was willing to believe in, if
either, so I added a parameter
called, if you believe in
momentum, then you should
change the price by -- And here
I just did something taking a
Gaussian times the last change,
and, in fact, added it in.
So if it went up yesterday, it
will more likely go up today,
because I'm throwing in a
positive number, otherwise
a negative number.
Notice that this is additive.
Because it's dealing
with yesterday's price.
Change, with the change.
OK, so that's why we're
dealing with that.
Now, here's where I
should've put in this
test that I had up here.
Get it out from there.
Because what I want to do is,
say if self dot price is less
than 0.01, I'm going to set
it to 0, just keep it there.
That doesn't solve the problem
we had before though, right?
Then I'm going to append
it, and keep the last
change for future use.
OK, people understand
what's going on here?
And then show history is just
going to produce a plot.
We've seen that a
million times before.
Any questions about this?
Well, I have a question?
Does it make any sense?
Is it going to work at all?
So now let's test it.
So, I now have this unit test
program called unit test stock.
I originally did not make it a
function, I had it in-line, and
I realized that was really
stupid, because I wanted
to do it a lot of times.
So it's got an internal
procedure, internal function,
local to the unit test,
that runs the simulation.
And it takes the set of stocks
to simulate, a fig, figure
number, this is going to print
a bunch of graphs, and I want
to say what graph it is,
and whether or not I
believe in big mo.
It sets the mean to 0, and then
for s in the stocks, it moves
it, giving it the bias and
the momentum, then it
shows the history.
And then computes the mean
of, getting me the mean
of all the stocks in it.
We've seen this sort of
thing many times before.
I've then got some constants.
By the way, I want to emphasize
that I've named these constants
to make it easier to change.
Starting with 20
stocks, 100 days.
And then what I do is, I stock
sub 1, stocks 1 will be the
empty list, stocks 2
is the empty list.
Why do you think I'm
starting with bias of 0?
Because, what do you think the
mean should be, if I simulate
various things that
the bias of 0?
I start $100 as the average
price of the stock,
what should the average
price of the stock be?
If my code is correct, what
should the average price be,
after say, 100 days,
if there's no bias.
Pardon?
100, exactly.
Since there's no upward
or downward bias.
They may fluctuate wildly, but
if I look at enough stocks, the
average should be
right around 100.
I don't know what the
average would be if I
chose a different bias.
It's a little bit complicated,
so I chose the simplest bias.
Important lesson, so that there
would be some predictability in
the results, and I would have
some, if you will, smoke test
for knowing whether or not
I was getting, my code
seemed to be working.
All right, and initially, well,
maybe initially, just to be
simple I'm going to start
momentum equal to false.
Because, again, it seems
simpler have a model where
there's no momentum.
I'm looking for the simplest
model possible for the
first time I run it.
And then we looked at this
little loop before, for i in
range number of stocks, I'm
going to create two different
lists of stocks, one where the
moves, or distributions, are
chosen from a uniform, and the
other where they're Gaussian.
Because I'm sort of curious as
to, again, which is the right
way to think about
this, all right?
And then, I'm going
to just call it.
We'll see what we get.
So let's do it.
Let's hope that all the changes
I mad have not introduced
a syntax error.
All right, well at least
it did something.
Let's see what it did.
So the test on the left, you'll
remember, was the one with test
one, I believe, was the uniform
distribution, and test
two is the Gaussian.
So, but let's, what
should we do first?
Well, let's do the smoke test
number one: is the mean more
or less what we expected?
Well, it looks like it's
dead on 100, which was our
initial price in test two.
And in test one it's a
little bit above 100.
But, we didn't do that many
stocks, or that many days,
so it's quite plausible
that it's correct.
But, just to be sure, not to be
sure, but just to increase my
confidence, I'm going
to just run it again.
Well, here I'm a little bit
below 100 and in two, and
test one a little bit
below 100 as well.
You remember last time was
a little bit above 100.
I feel pretty good about this,
and in fact I ran it a lot
of times in my office.
And it just bounces around,
hovering around 100.
Course, this is the
wrong way to do it.
I should really just put it in
a nice test harness, where I
run 100, 200, 1,000 trials, but
I didn't want to bore
you with that here.
So we'll see that, OK, we
passed the first smoke test.
We seem to be where
we expect to be.
Well, let's try smoke test two.
What else might we want
to see, to see if we got
things working properly?
Well, I kind of ignored the
notion of bias by making it
0, so let's give it
a big bias here.
Assuming it will
let me edit it.
We just gotta start it
up again, it's the
safest thing to do.
You wouldn't think I would
have, I don't have -- all
right, be that way about it.
Fortunately, we've been
through this before.
We know if we
relaunch the Finder.
Who says Mac OS is flawless?
All right, we were down here,
and I was saying, let's try
a larger, introduce a bias.
Again, we're trying to
see if it does what
we think it might do.
So what do you think it
should do with a bias?
Where should the mean be now?
Still around 100?
Or higher, right?
Because we've now put
in a bias suggesting
that it should go up.
Oops.
It wouldn't have hurt it.
All right.
So let's run it.
Sure enough, for one, we see,
test two, it's a little bit
over 100, and for test
one it's way over 100.
Well, let's make sure
it's not a fluke.
Try it again.
So, sure enough, changing
the bias changed the price,
and even changed it in
the right direction.
So we can feel pretty
comfortable that it's doing
something good with that.
We could also feel pretty
comfortable that that's
probably way too
high a bias, right?
We would not expect that the
mean should be over 160, or
in one case, 150, after only
100 days trading, right?
Things don't typically
go up 50% in 100 days.
They go down 50%, but --
All right, so that's good.
Oh, let's look at
something else now.
Let's go back to where,
a simpler bias here.
We'll run it again.
And think about, what's the
difference between the
Gaussian and the normal?
Can we deduce anything
about those?
Not, well, let me ask you.
What do you think, yes or no?
Anybody see anything
interesting here?
Yeah?
STUDENT: The variance of the
Gaussian seems to be less than
the variance of the uniform.
PROFESSOR: The variance
of the Gaussian --
STUDENT: -- is less.
PROFESSOR: So all right, that
appears to be the case here.
But let's run it again,
as we've done with
all the other tests.
So we have a hypothesis.
Let's not fall victim to
the Oklahoma sharpshooter.
We'll test our hypothesis, or
at least examine it again,
see if it's, in some
sense, repeatable.
Well, now what do we see?
Doesn't seem to be true
this time, right?
Not obviously.
So, we're not sure about this.
So this is something
that we would need to
investigate further.
And we would need, to have to
look at it, and it's going to
be very tricky, by the way, as
to what the right answer is.
But if you think about it, it
would not be surprising if the
Gaussians, at least, gave us
some surprising, more extreme,
results, than the uniform.
Because the uniform, as we've
set it up here, is bounded.
The minimum and the
maximum is bounded.
With the Gaussian,
there's a tail.
And you might every once in a
while get this, at least as
we've done it in this case,
this large move out at the end.
You might not.
There's nothing profound about
this, other than the
understanding that the details
of how you set these things
up can matter a lot.
Well, the final thing I want
to look at is momentum.
So let's go back, and let's
set mo to true here.
Well, doesn't want us to
Ah, there it does.
So, and now let's run it
and see what happens.
What do you think
should happen?
Anybody?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: I think
you're right.
These ones should curl, see
if I can -- oh, not bad.
Let's run it.
Well, it's a little hard
to see, but things
tend to take off.
Because once things started
moving, it tends to
move in that direction.
All right.
How do we go about choosing
these parameters?
How do we go about
deciding what to do?
Well, we play with it, the way
I've been playing with it, and
compare the results to
some set of real data.
And then we try and get our
simulation to match the past,
and hope that that will
help it predict the future.
We're not enough time
to go through all the,
to do that a lot.
I will be posting code that you
can play with, and I suggest
you go through exactly
this kind of exercise.
Because this is really
the way that people do
develop simulations.
They don't, out of whole cloth,
get it right the first time.
They build them, they do what
if games, they play with them,
and then they try and adjust
them to get them right.
The nice thing here is, you can
decide whether you believe
momentum and see what it would
mean, or not mean, etc.
All right, one more lecture.
See you guys next week.